我係。
好。
有冇其他嘅提名？
哦。
我哋而家選副主席。
仲有冇其他嘅提名？
都夠鍾啦，噉啊，開始我哋嘅會議。
由提名書由一位委員口頭提出，一名委員獲議，姚思榮議員。
噉啊！如果冇其他嘅提名咧，噉就數三聲，一二三，噉就。
噉啊，恭喜啊林建峯議員啦！咁接下嚟，我亦都交畀你繼續主持個會議啊！
林建峯議員咧就自動當選咧，係成為小組嘅主席。
阿林建峯議員，好。阿石烈謙議員獲議嘅。阿林建峯議員接唔接受提名？我接受。好。
啊！多謝各位支持。噉啊，而家咧就係啊，我想問一問大家，需唔需要選一位副主席？
噉啊！第一項議程咧就選舉呢一個嘅誒聯合小組委員會嘅主席啊，要啲乜啊？
啊，OK，大家認為係啊，應該選一位副主席嘅。噉我就係已經有人啊和議咗啦。咁而家咧就進進行二零一八年至二零一九年度立法會會期聯合小組委員會副主席嘅選舉。
等我講完先啊！好痛啊，大佬！嗱，而家進行二零一八至一九年度誒立法會會期監察西九文化區計劃噉啊推行情況聯合小組委員會主席嘅選舉。根據在於內務手則附件四嘅選舉程序咧，而家請委員提名主席一職嘅人選，有。
陳志全議員。
啊！大家有咩意見？
誒委員。
係，阿和議，阿石禮謙議員。
謝偉全議員，即我提名吳永嘉議員。
委員喺選舉票上，如果蓋咗印之後咧。
不記名，不記名。哦，不記名，哦，不記名嘅啦，我哋我就要派選票啦。O K。
吳永嘉議員，你接唔接受？誒，我接受主席。好，咁誒，有冇其他嘅提名？
大家舉手啦，好嘛？啊，不記不記名。噉啊，首先啊，黃碧雲議員。
我係會宣佈投票程序結束嘅。咁而家咧就啊，我首先咧就請工作人員啦派發呢個選票。
謝謝偉全議員，啊明明我先啊，麥都開咗。秘書同我講嘅，因為我睇住個稿，所以秘書話畀我聽邊個先咧，我就邊個先。
噉啊！如果係冇其他嘅提名咧，我哋就要啊，我哋可以以不記名嘅方式投票，或者係以記名嘅方式。
噉就誒透過毛孟靜議員咧，就啊啊黃碧雲議員咧就話係誒會接受呢個提名嘅，有冇其他提名？
有效提名咧係需由一名委員口頭作出，並由最少另外一名委員口頭附議。而家咧就啊請啊委員提名，冇。
啊！阿阿謝偉全議員咧，讓畀你，讓畀阿毛孟靜議員睇。毛孟靜議員，碧雲議員就抱歉咧，佢今日嚟唔到呢個會議，但係佢同我誒講得一清二楚咧，佢係接受誒提名嘅。好，誒有冇人和議？
都未夠。
唔應該話會後。
唔好離開個座位。
如果大家，
咁誒，根據內務手則。
噉啊！請兩位嘅。
張華峯行唔過㗎。
而家請委員咧，喺選票上。
啊！候選人嘅偏好依次序為。
啊，屬意候選人嘅編號旁邊啦，蓋上一個tick字。
誒一咧就係黃碧雲議員，二咧就係吳永嘉議員。
提名人啊出嚟監票好嘛？阿武孟正議員同埋謝偉全議員。
請兩位提名人，武孟正議員同埋謝偉全議員上嚟啦，係監票嘅。
嗱，由於依個係不記名嘅投票，請大家唔啊唔需要將選票向其他人展示。
每名候選人係會按獲提名嘅先後次序而獲啊編配一個候選人嘅編號。
填咗選票嘅，噉我請工作人員啊收翻啲選票，OK啦嘛，OK。總共派出咗十二票嘅。啊，我哋工作人員咧總共係啊派出咗十二張票嘅。
噉啊，當大家完成咗吸引嘅程序咧，噉就啊所有獲得發選票嘅委員會咧，就係需要啊親自將呢個選票咧就放入呢個投票箱。委員如果未將選票放入投票箱咧，就請你哋。
叫佢。
嗯。
公正。
以後。
原來。
二號。
一號。
好中意衝擊主席啊！
主席，我哋需要長表。好，唔該。
所以所以張華鋒議員如果入嚟咧，要讓個旁邊嘅位畀佢。
嗰度未跟到，跟唔到。曾阿哥，等陣等陣，佢嗰度跟唔。即係話唱咗三個㗎。唱咗三個，三個二號。兩位確認嚇，三個，嗯。
我哋。
誒一。
二號。
啊，噉啊。
黃碧雲議員四票，吳永嘉議員八票。
喺立法會C、B括弧一。
O.K.啊，噉我哋進入去。
一五誒縮十八至十九括弧零一嘅文件咧，政府當局咧就建議咗。
跟住咧就係誒，我就想誒委員咧提出誒，我哋今個年度誒討論嘅事項，咁誒。
我哋下一次先至，或者我書面啦，我同各方面check咗之後咧，再書面畀大家啊確定嗰個會議日期，好嗎？OK，噉啊。
有關嘅方面再check一check，而確認呢幾個日子係可以嘅。咁不過個預留咗房間嘅日子咧，就已經派發咗畀大家啦。咁如果你哋有啲咩意見咧，都可以啊提出嚟嘅。
派出嘅選票咧係十二張，我哋收翻嚟嘅咧亦都係十二張。咁咧就黃碧雲議員啦係得到四票，誒吳永嘉議員係得到八票。咁咧就吳永嘉議員咧係當選副主席嘅。誒，恭喜你。噉啊，請你。
誒，以情第二嘅就係誒秘書處咧，就已經將誒二零一九年一月至到二零一九年六月期間誒，佢哋預留咗誒幾個兩小時嘅會議時段。咁嗱，依個咧，我誒稍後我會再同秘書check一check，亦都會上誒。
O.K.
串連唔到嗰個整個嘅畫面咯。
嗱，啊嗱，其實啊，依兩個題目咧都。
嗱，我我聽到啊，抗議員嗰個意見，我響會後咧會同西九嗰方面傾。
西九文化區係啊提供嘅，噉我覺得大家都可以可以好焗係啊。首先，江俊宇議員。
睇下可唔可以早啲傾呢個有關呢個西九嘅財務問題？石禮謙議員，主席，我都係喺覺誒覺得咧，四月咧係有少少遲啲，同埋同時而家我哋喺呢個呢個小組裏邊最突。
啊，跟住咧就政府當局咧亦都建議咗一啲討論嘅事項嘅。咁呢個咧就係啊啊，在於立法會C B括弧一一五縮十八至十九括弧零一嘅文件嘅。
啊，一係列嘅事項嘅咁嗰個啊，大家都可以睇到㗎啦。咁另外啊，立法會啊C B括弧一一一五short十八至十九啊括弧零二號文件咧，亦都有一係列嘅跟進事項。
噉啊，如果啊委員同意聯合小組委員會按照上述時間表，所謂上述時間表咧，就我哋稍後會確認嘅舉行會議咧。下一次會議就啊暫定咧，就係響二零一九年一月十四日星期一。
一下晝嘅四點三十分舉行嘅，咁政府當局咧亦都係建議喺依次嘅會議咧討論啊兩個事項嘅。第一個就係西九文化區嘅文化軟件發展同埋西九文化兩區嘅最新發展。請問啊，委員有咩意見？
噉我哋就啊，係啊，我一個考慮就整個西九文化區咧，因為咁龐大嘅一個工程，就事實有香港人咧繼續擔心就又變大白象。嗱，誒，故宮咧就因為係馬會資助，就誒，可可唔可以咧就另外即係？
突出咁自己一套嚟傾，其他嗰啲我希望有啲宏觀啲嘅誒財政上啊、工程上嘅考慮。就而家我感覺係一節一節嘅，誒呢一節就講M加，嗰一節就講戲曲中心，再一節就講誒藝術廳噉。咁大家就一節節咧係。
啊，包括咗呢個啊，故宮嗰個項目嘅。咁另外有關財務嗰度咧，噉啊，亦都多謝阿毛議員提出呢個問題。其實咧，啊暫定咧，我哋就安排咗有一個討論嘅時間嘅。噉就係會響四月嗰個時間討論嘅。噉啊嗱，呢個相關政策咧。
問大家對於嗰個項目同埋個時間有咩建議？噉啊，而家嗰個暫定咧就係四月啦。咁主要咧就係啊討論西九文化區計劃最新嘅財務狀況。咁呢個係整體嘅嚇。如果有啲咩啊其他嘅細節嘢，大家係想。
誒，主席，我想係即係表達一個可能市民都相當關心啦。而家，因為其實就因為而家嗰個教早前嗰個嘅財務啦，甚至我哋稱之為一啲嘅醜聞啦，噉樣。咁其實就好多人都擔心，如果你話頭先聽主席咧，就話啊，可能係四月嘅時間，我係提出一個擔憂，即係會唔會太遲，會唔會？
嗱，依個。
噉啊！
傾到十一點十五分鐘嘅。
以前咧，我哋就係。
大家都有個名單㗎啦，寫唔寫我？
啊！讀一讀個名單出嚟，唔需要。
啊，有關嘅官員同埋西九管理區嘅代表啊，進入會議室。
乎係遲啲啦，主席。係啊，多謝啊，食議員啊，我我諗好好清晰。
嗱，首先咧，我係啊歡迎政府當局同埋西九管理局嘅代表出席今日嘅會議。
首先咧，我係會請啊政府同埋啊啊西九嘅代表咧，就介紹嘅啊。
問題或者意見，如果冇咧，我哋就啊進落去進入去下一個議程，就係西九文化區發展進度嘅彙報。噉啊，或者我哋首先請。
到時又洗濕咗個頭啦，咁定還先？之前會唔會可以有多啲資料我哋即係去掌握咧？因為呢個都係普遍市民關心，就係成個即係藝術區嗰個走向，同埋一啲財務嗰啲走法，你搞唔搞得掂嘅噉樣？會唔會有機會喺可能一月或者再之前嘅時間有啲資料披露到咧？唔該，主席。
誒最重要咧，我哋睇下佢財務，佢幾時係budget？應該佢哋已經有一個時間喺度。佢直接到當我哋今次第一次開會好，第二次開會好，佢都應該有個文件畀我哋睇下，佢財務嘅情況係點？佢幾時要去要嚟立法會攞錢？要即係如果你等到四月咧，接
啊！我亦都正話啊，回答啊，抗議員嗰陣時咧講咗咧，我會後會立即同西九啊嘅管理層咧就要求佢哋睇下可唔可以盡早睇下幾時嚟立嚟，我哋呢個委員會嗰度咧就啊講講佢哋嘅財務情況啊，石石。其實我同意你誒，你同我可以同。
但叫畀張文件，我哋講講目前，目前而家個誒佢依個financial position係點嘅情況喺度。噉你啊一月再講唔緊要，我哋都睇到即係喺度喺我哋面前都有啲誒文件，我哋可以跟進啊。O K，好多謝啊，食源嘅意見，有冇其他？
一個。
嗯。
阿司徒先生。
文化區嘅發展進度。
啊，跟住係請啊！
Thank you, Duncan. Thank you, Chairman. Good morning to members. So we have a few slides around ten minutes to take you through the development of where we are and what we're planning.
多項文化藝術嘅設施咧，亦都會誒進入籌劃嘅階段啦。包括我哋所謂嘅A.C.E.，即係藝術商業同埋展覽發展組合，同埋藝術家旅社公寓同埋音樂中心。
course, so please put that date into your diary because of course tickets are very very hard to get, and we've reserved some for you. So, but with that, I'll pass that on to Jeremy and he'll take us through the presentation. Thank you. Yeah, well, thank you for the invitation.
秘書長係咪？你首先作一個介紹啊？誒，多謝主席，係我首先做一個簡單嘅介紹，然後請誒西九嘅行政總裁柏志高先生再補充嘅誒。主席，由於今日係聯會小組委員會喺呢一屆立法會第第一次會議，所以我哋好希望咧借住誒今次嘅誒會議咧係。
會簡單介紹西九文化區嘅整體嘅發展進展嘅噉我我留意到剛才大家嘅討論咧，亦都有部分嘅議員咧係希望係一個誒鳥瞰式嘅總體發展嘅概況嘅瞭解噉，我諗今日就係一個好好嘅機會啦。咁西九文化區嘅項目咧，而家由建造階段咧逐步買。
去營運嘅階段，咁好多項嘅文化藝術嘅設施亦都喺度興建，包括一戲曲中心、二M家大樓、三藝術公園同埋自由空間、四香港故宮文化博物院、五係演藝綜合劇場同埋綜合地庫，以及六係公共基礎嘅設施工程。
咁戲曲中心咧喺今年年底咧就會啟用㗎啦，而藝術公園咧亦都喺今年年初起咧係分階段開放。未來數年間咧，我哋會陸續落成嘅設施咧，仲包括有自由空間啦、M加博物館啦、香港故宮博物館同埋係綜合演藝劇場嘅。除咗興建中嘅設施之外咧，
隨住西九文化區投入營運咧，誒，我哋相信佢會為香港帶嚟文化、社會同埋經濟各方面嘅效益嘅，亦都可以為年青人咧創造更加多元嘅誒文化創意嘅機遇嘅。咁接下嚟咧，我就請阿柏志高先生用投影片去更加詳細介紹先佢西九。
多謝好啊！請阿柏志高先生。Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Good morning, everybody. A couple of things, just to echo what the permanent secretary has just said. This presentation is intended to give members an overview of the situation. We will, of course, be coming back with more details to be able to discuss in.
個個project，subsequently and indeed the second paper today deals with the CITU centre in more detail. I'd also like to pick up on a question about our financial situation. I'm happy to provide our annual report, which provides the latest information on our financial situation, and I think we've already tabled it in Legco. But
We'll make sure you get a copy of that. Obviously, that that is the latest position that we have, so that's probably the best reference for members at this stage. I will be asking Jeremy to take us through the the presentation in a second, dealing with all of those facilities that we are currently.
working on, we won't at this stage be focusing on the upcoming facilities, but I do want to emphasise that we're not stopping at what we've got. There's a lot more to come, and that that forward-looking approach is really where we are coming from now. But I do want to add a couple of final points, particularly in.
O.K.
Frozen，isn't it？
very slow.
嗯。
謝謝， Duncan。
little bit of a delay.
And yes, that's about ready.
just waiting for it to appear on the screen.
So, just moving on to the next slide.
文化及藝術建築，which are the colourful ones， we're also looking at how we take those commercial buildings forward.
Our facilities management team, the performing arts team and our security team are all moving into the building currently, all in anticipation of the the first performance, as CEO mentioned, in January.
So the next slide, this is just a visual of the the grand theatre. So obviously all the seatings in place that we have in the theatre on on the two levels, disabled facilities as well for universal accessibility is included.
So just up on the screen there is a visual of all of the facilities that we're currently delivering and intend to deliver. I think you can see there's 14, some 14 projects in total.
我們會邀請成員到訪該中心，就像每年的這個時候一樣。我們會盡快安排這個活動，大概在這個月的最後或下個月的初。我還想邀請成員參加1月20日的中心開幕典禮。我們會寄發邀請函給你們。
嗯。
But you can see around, we're still finishing off the part, so there's still a sort of construction area.
And a couple of the artistic art shelters that we we have also in the park.
Next slide is the tea house theatre. Again, this is completed. It'll have
And we also have the seminar seminar hall, which is which is also fitted out with the seating as well on the floors above.
Again, just a view from the east to the west. You can see some further RDE facilities and free space that's in the background.
Loose chairs and tables in, and a sort of VIP area also at the top for performances and with dim sum as well.
Just a few pictures of the various rooms, studio. Obviously, the interior and the exterior of the studio on the floors above.
who basically had access to the site from around the seventeenth of September, so we've been on site around six weeks.
This area here is the ticket office. This has been open for some weeks now, following the press conference that we gave, and I believe there'll be an update on on the ticket situation in the follow-up item on the agenda.
This is the Free Space building itself, and you can see there on the Free Space building the big projection screen, which we will have images on from the from the main lawn.
So here we have the main atrium, the sort of public area which will be open, also called the plaza, where we hope to do some future performances as well. And the ticket office is already in this area, which the public are currently using today.
Across the development, Zichu obviously being on the the furthest on the right hand side, and right across to the Palace Museum on the on the left hand side of that. Sorry, Jeremy, if I can just add, I do want to point out the grey buildings. We're not ignoring the grey buildings; those are the commercial developments. But today we're focusing on
There we go. So yes, this is the Z two centre, which we should be issuing the substantial completion of works certificate this month. And a lot of the final fit out and the integration of all the theatre systems is ongoing.
So that's ZHU. If we just move on to the art park, which has seen very good progress through two thousand and eighteen, we've already had it's being delivered in three phases. We've already had phase one open to the public, which they've been enjoying for some time now with the the promenade.
And we will be looking to open up the phase two in December, towards the end of the year. You can see there the very large lawn in the middle, which has already been used for some free space events and has been fairly successful.
嗯。
and hence we're moving forward.
到再clamation sites。
which again closes the building up.
this is this is one of the government funded contracts.
And I can report that good progress has been made on this project. We actually have.
So just a couple of views there. That's from the south side. You can see the facade, which is going on the tower.
你可以見到，有啲鏟土
Similarly, this is a view from the north. Again, you can see the facade halfway halfway up the tower there.
The main podium deck, as a structure, is almost complete, and we will now push forward with the cladding to the podium deck.
This is the contract currently on site, which is excavating all the basement, the integrated basement below the Lyric Theatre.
And you can see there on the tower that we're just very close to the topping out of that tower, which should happen by the end of November.
just a little bit more workers back onto site than we had when we terminated on the 17th, so we're almost back to full strength, but
Moving on to the lyric theatre, the lyric theatre is split into it's the lyric theatre and the extended basement. It's split into two works contracts.
One is to do the excavation of all the basement below, and the second contract is to build the superstructure of the lyric itself. And I'm pleased to say that we've made good progress with with both those contracts.
This is a visual from the harbour side, and you can see we have retail dining and entertainment facilities all along the waterfront, with the landscaping and the promenade. And these RDE facilities will be fitted out in the in the months ahead.
Okay, moving on to the M Plus building. As members will know, we terminated the contract for this facility, the main construction contract, on the seventeenth of August, and we have since appointed a management contractor.
With the programme growing forward and with our endeavours to deliver the building and open it by the end of 2020, obviously there'll be a lot to do in 2019. But we're pleased to say a lot of the subcontractors have been novated over that were previously working on the project.
And ADRG.
六百個座位。
In the medium theatre.
所以你可以睇到咧，個設計。
And you can see there the the foyer.
A view towards the auditorium.
The sort of staircase leading to the balcony area.
This is designed by UN Studios.
just a couple of further pictures of the excavation and lateral supports.
That is the view from the stage itself, looking out towards the auditorium.
This is an image from inside, looking out towards the harbour.
And this should start on around the 19th, 20th of November.
And you can see there the view towards the stage from the main auditorium.
And we also have two other theatres. This is a three-theatre facility. We have the medium theatre.
And then the small studio theatre, which is also in this facility, two hundred, two hundred odd seats.
around the site.
You can see here an aerial picture.
Thank you, members. Happy to take any questions.
So that should be open, as I say, early January.
And that's a digital rendering of the architectural form of the building.
So package one is almost completed. It'll be finished in the next one to two months.
This is located just on the sort of north west of the park. You can see there on the bottom right hand corner.
And the main works, which has been out to tender for some months, is due to return in the next few weeks for award in the sort of first second quarter of 2019.
So the lyric theatre itself, we've completed all of the design, and it's been tendered out, and we're just in the final process of awarding that contract to a preferred main contractor.
度啊啊有幾多咧？畀個時間表嚟講下，即係會拖延再啊啊三個月啊、半年啊等等。咁同埋啊，牽涉嘅公共財政上嘅損失又有幾多咧？因為你唔可以啊。
Package two, which is the connection with Austin Road West Station, started on site a few months ago, and that will provide a link through to the Zju Centre to be finished in 2020.
Okay, final few slides. We're on to the Palace Museum, and you can see the overall progress here. The site that is in the middle of the screen, the foundations are almost completed, and we're just about to start on some of the excavation and lateral support.
Final couple of slides. PIW, the public infrastructure works. We have three packages. One is the hall road and the utilities, which go around our site. We also have the subway at Austin at Zigu Center, and obviously the Artist Square Bridge.
Finally, the temporary pavilion, which was a young persons architectural competition that we had, which was quite public. The construction of this has been going smoothly, and we will be aiming to have that completed in early January, and then open.
哇，thank you，Mr. Stoll。啊，而家咧就係誒議員咧誒提問嘅時間。噉啊，我建議咧就每位四分鐘。咁依一個啦，亦亦都係連問連答嘅。噉啊，首先啦，我讀一讀啦。報咗名嘅咧就有毛孟靜議員、陳志全議員、譚文浩議。
議員、亢進宇議員、劉國芬議員、姚思榮議員同埋郭嘉琪議員嘅，噉就每位四分鐘。咁首先係請阿毛孟靜議員。啊唔該，主席，就有家有關M加嗰度咧，個承建商新昌就真係啊，當初點解政府會畀一個承建商係會？
係。
Money paid in excess of what they are owed.
秘書長或者你睇下，可唔可以答一答故宮三十五億嗰個問題？
But certainly there has been an impact. They will also be giving us a revised costing for the balance of the payments. Now let me stress two things on on payments.
會員工，因為如果設計又唔係真係咁複雜，又唔係話好高嘅誒一個建築物，點解要成四年嘅時間嘅咧？啊，四年幾咧？或者嚇，可唔可以誒講一講？唔該。好，誒秘書長。
But of course, the fact that we've had delays, the fact that we've had this termination, will have an impact on our the financial situation going forward, and that's why we've given the new management contractor till December to come up with the new figures.
搞到誒畀唔到錢嘅，咁點解仍然冇將佢誒由嗰個認可公共工程承建商嘅名冊嗰度剔除咧？呢個係我哋嘅疑問。而第二咧，就因呢啲錢銀問題，由停工到復工之間影響嘅工程進
你睇到嘅嗰個管理局，你畀代佢畀又唔係，唔代佢畀又唔係。咁但係另外就有話啊，仍然嘈緊話你爭好多新窗爭佢哋好多錢啊，誒七千萬啊等等。呢個嗰個而家個情況係點咧？呢係所有係有關M家嘅問題。
我再誒一次想清楚問咧，故宮嗰度馬會就啊畀錢㗎，個三十五億就係咪有冇上限嘅？如果第日有追加撥款啊、超支啊、什麼就一定唔會翻嚟啊財委會攞錢嘅，係唔係咧？咁雖然我都理解馬會嘅錢咧，其實好多。
多時都係包括喺啊公共嘅財產之內嘅。對我嘅理解就係啊，你都係做好多嘅慈善啊等等。誒點解會噉嘅咧？誒係係呢個可唔可以承諾咧？然誒有關故宮第二個問題就係二零一六年底宣佈嘅，而家就話二零二一年咧就預計。
誒或者我簡單誒，首首首先答答顧工嗰度先啦，因為其實誒，啊，我想知M家先，我係噉樣問緊個嚇，因為其他我會畀其他同事答。咁如果無議員想順序嘅，噉我首先請誒土木工程發展處謝調利民政事務局嘅應分方總監去答答關於M家新窗個問題。
好唔該，誒，多謝主席。就住M加新窗嗰個問題咧，其實咧就誒發展局咧，亦都係一向咧係密切監視住新窗嗰個財務嗰個財政嗰個方面嘅問題嘅，或者議員都會明白到咧，其實新窗咧喺沙中線土瓜環誒站呢個私谷問題上高咧，已經係被。
誒暫停咧，係投標依個資格嘅，係維期四個月嘅，係由今年嘅十月八號啊，係生效嘅。噉係其實喺依段時間裏邊咧，我我瞭解到咧，係發展局亦都係繼繼續咧，係密切係誒監誒監察住新窗嗰個財務情況。如果而家係同時再執行依個罰則咧。
for essentially a tripartite arrangement. In other words.
That were previously employed by Xin Chong, but I must stress, of course.
生過程係係點樣嘅？即係係係點樣去揾呢個更替誒？
They decide which subcontractors and contractors need to be novated to ensure the completion of the project.
子合併的
跟住係陳志全議員，係誒唔該主席，即係今日我哋呢個項目本來係講整個西九嘅進度彙報，就應該討論闊啲嘅，但係。
I would add that we are we are obviously trying to get as full a picture as we can as to the liability for those subcontractors.
分判商出嚟㗎，咁未來如果都再遇到即係大家利是，唔知拍攝公司有冇聽大家利是啫？即係即係再發生呢啲呢啲touch wood嚇，再發生呢啲，你哋有冇一個？
安全性啊，等等，咁所以個設計係比較複雜嘅，同埋因為亦都要配合整體西九一個城市中的花園嘅設計咧，喺嗰個路誒路嘅面啊，同埋地底啊等等咧，個要求嗰個工程嘅複雜性係大好多嘅。
係變咗係無效嘅，噉我哋會睇翻係四個月之後咧。咁如果係新槍仍然都係嗰財務上高係有問題嘅話咧，咁發展工會根據誒個手則嚟講咧，可以將誒新槍咧係繼續暫時取消佢競投嘅資格啦，或者降級啦，去到試用級別咧，甚至咧或者係降低呢個。
組別嘅咁或者可以更加誒慎嘅話咧，就係從嗰個認可名冊上邊咧去取名嘅。咁依依一啲咧，亦都係視乎翻新窗跟住依幾個月嗰個提供畀發展局嘅資料咧，去再釐定究竟應該係點採取乜嘢適當行動嘅。你哋而家理解工程時間表同埋啊，我哋財政上嘅損失。
係啦，我唔接受。睇睇下，Mr. Peskov。Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Yes, there has been an impact. This is something that we'll be working with the newly appointed management contractor. We've set them a deadline by December to give us the information as to what they see will be the revised timetable.
We have only been paying for work done, so where work has been done by the subcontractor or the contractor, we've ensured that they are paid for that work. That also applies to work done by previously Sinchong. In other words, all of their work had to be certified before we paid any money to them. So they have not had.
誒我諗誒我好快講講啦。誒咁個故宮嘅誒頭先啊，毛萬靜議員就擔心嗰個故宮嘅興建啦。咁其實個時間表其實都係已經頗緊逼嘅，因為起一個博物館咧唔同起普通嘅大廈，因為佢個儲藏要話好好嘅要求啦，因為温度濕度啦，咁同埋嗰個運送啊安。
奈何咧？因為新窗事件咧，我哋都係要問清楚啲。不過，我先講幾句啦，即係我都係西九文化區嘅用家，好有經驗，好豐富。我哋啱啱月底上個月底先至喺誒西九度搞咗拼多噉，都好好成功嘅。咁但係我希望即係我哋都有多啲機會，呢啲主辦單位同西九去作。
一啲檢討evaluation，即係從用家嘅角度去畀翻多啲意見，畀西九即係未來可以多啲改善啦。噉我要問翻，即係都係新槍事件啦，即係到底而家誒新被新槍拖欠嘅分判商同埋金額有究竟有幾多？清而家係咪仲係拖緊好多嘅咧？因為頭先阿柏志高。
先生就話做起曬咁先至誒會由即係西九去比嘅，即係本來我就想問，其實個原則係點樣？即係點解一啲係由分判商繼續要等佢即係比，一啲就係由西西九比咁嗰個邏輯係點樣？咁同埋咧呢份誒叫做更替分判商咧，佢個產
唔該，主席。
譚文浩議員。
你就聽farewell。
identified and certified by.
有七間嘅subcontractor。
Mr. Prescott. Yes, I got paid very well. Thank you.
我想問柏志高先生同你身邊西九管理局嘅團隊，上個月有冇出糧？你自己？
I'm told by my team this has only ever happened once before in Hong Kong, so we've been very, very unlucky.
However, where work has been done, and we've made this statement very publicly, and can be certified to have been done, in other words, it can be checked and verified, then we will of course pay for that work.
即係話，Mr. Prescott講到嗰啲咧，就係新窗同佢個contractor嗰個關係。不過，阿Mr. Prescott，我都係誒請你答一答，你可唔可以？你知唔知道，或者有啲咩你係知道可以誒向陳議員講講嘅咧？
case，the situation between when we appointed them as our main contractor，and when they obviously fell into insolvency was a matter of years，and you can't anticipate that sort of situation，but we we do our best to try and investigate。
進一步嘅機制去，即係唔好似上次噉嘅嚇，好似我哋覺得你又唔向人匯報誒，自己喺裏邊搞掂咗啲問題咁咧。唔該，主席。誒，Mr.Pescott，Thank you。The arrangements for innovation are actually provided for under the contract with Sinchong. They provide
When a subcontractor is identified to be essential for the completion of the project, we would approach the subcontractor, offer them innovation. If they agree, we then approach Sinchong and ask them to sign off the rights that they had previously under the contract, and then the third party is a whole.
要pay for the continuing liability under the under the contracts. The issue in terms of choices as to who should be chosen and who is not that's a matter that is between the management contractor, the contract administrator, and of course my team.
The contract, unfortunately, is between Sinchong and the subcontractors. What we're offering now is a new state under the terms of the contract. The other question in terms of what happens if this happens again, I agree with you. It'll never happen again. That would be absolutely the worst, the worst thing. Apparently.
Having said that, I can tell you that we have of course instituted even stronger financial checks on all of our contractors going forward. We do that now through a third-party investigation to try and ensure that the company is solvent throughout. But frankly, in this
啊，跟住主席，主席阿柏志高先生，其實佢冇講，佢頭先就話啲分判新槍爭嗰啲分判商，好似佢冇佢佢係唔會掌握，唔會知道。咁喺咩情況之下，你先會畀錢？係咪嗰啲分判商舉手啊，即係死得噉樣，你先至會畀錢？你而家話你唔知新槍同埋嗰啲誒分判商之間嘅瓜葛？
Mr. Chairman, the the situation is that, as I said, we're trying to find out the the the relationship. Previously, I'm told that there were something like five hundred subcontractors and service providers employed by Sinchong for this contract. That's a huge number that have to be identified. Their work.
contract administrator etc. so that process does take time. As far as those that are not innovated, of course, they still have recourse to seek their full compensation under the terms of their contract with Sinchong. That that contract remains. That's that's not something that we can involve with.
呢答。
喺。
財委會。
就係攞翻。
全部都係。
你有講過就係話。
佢哋嘅員工點樣咧？
你喺上一次。
你嘅答案係噉樣嘅。
嘅會議有個transcript嘅。
佢哋嘅入閘紙，佢哋做咗嘅嘢。
爭七千萬，噉佢哋有冇pay翻咯？
我特別清楚問你：啲員工有冇出到糧？
你睇唔睇到呢一答？你話係可以certify知道做咗嘅works。
二零一七年十二月八號同埋二零一八年嘅一月五號嘅兩次。
fair manner.
Mr. Peskov.
There have been instances where subcontractors have.
第一，我 never lie to Legislative Council.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. A couple of things.
在terms of the quantum of their claims， that has to be checked。
Where was I? Oh yes, in terms of the the subcontractors.
and I can confirm that those payment are being made on a monthly basis. Then what is this?
The information I had, you read it out yourself. Clearly demonstrated that they were being paid, and that the money was going to the to the workers.
究竟係柏志高先生，你又再次喺呢度講大話，定係你根本又再次證明你嘅無能？你連爭人幾多錢你都唔知。
We have had instances where subcontractors.如果係呢一個係事實嘅話，如果呢一個係事實嘅話，你你畀阿阿Mr.好，moment sorry，I think it's only fair I have a chance to reply.
我 have never lied in the thirty odd years I've been coming to the Legislative Council, and I have no intention to do so now. The facts, as stated in my previous reports in January and December, are correct.
七千幾萬七個contractor，你由二零一七年嘅二月已經開始直接畀錢呢一啲嘅分判商，咁點解呢啲會收唔到錢？
The situation in respect of those seven contractors, again, we have actually been in touch with them. We are working through the process to ensure that where they have done work that can be certified, they will be paid for that work. That process is under as ongoing as I've already reported.
跟住就又再講另外一次會咧，你又話The payment are going to the workers. I in fact subsequently checked after the meeting to make sure that those payments were going to the workers through the contractor and subcontractors.
I can certainly confirm that, as far as our checking is concerned, all the workers are being paid on time. I can also confirm that, as far as our checking is concerned, the contractors that are working on our sites currently have the resources to continue their work.
submitted claims that are not verifiable, and of course, as we're paying with public money, we have to be sure that those claims are properly verified and paid out. But I can assure you, these subcontractors, the seven that you've identified plus, I think we've got 60 odd that we're still dealing with, they will be resolved in due course in a in a fair
跟住係康俊宇議員。
啊，李司長。
噉你知唔知自己爭人幾多錢嘅咧？唔該，主席。
我哋而家同個分判商嗰度仍然係對緊數嘅嚇，噉你有冇check啊？
好，你而家就話你係會去解決同埋同佢哋傾，但喺之前呢幾個contractor點樣畀你哋威逼啊？你哋人哋有一個爭三千萬，你攞住三百萬同人講話，你收咗就收聲，你籤埋呢份嘢就算數。我係最後一句説話，我想問政府官員柏志高噉樣有冇失職？
誒多謝主席，多謝議員。誒，我諗咧，其實喺建築界入邊咧，誒，當個發展商畀咗嗰個誒主要承判商咧，係主要承判商去揾一啲分判商嘅。咁嗰個法係西九管理局去monitor住佢有冇畀到錢啊嘛。佢另外都有講過，就係話佢係有check過㗎。
佢有睇啲reset㗎，如果有睇啲reset嘅，點解爭咗七千萬爭咗年幾啊？你等下秘書長答我先啦，正話黑刺煲先生咧亦都答著咧，就話如果係有一啲單據咧，佢哋係要誒查證咗，然後先畀錢嘅。咁中間有冇時間嘅誒拖？
慢咗啦，嗱咁呢個我我我哋稍後可以再。我我只係好想簡單補充補充兩句啫。其實喺一個咁大嘅contract咧，其實有成超過五百幾個分判商咧，其實呢個都係比較上係少有嘅。咁期間咧，誒西九佢直接同一啲分判商喺今年年。
初二月開始，直接係誒就開啲分判商。佢其實都係一部分係話對於西九呢個M加工程係最重要個決嘅。當然咧，其實呢個主要承判商佢可能揾到一啲嘅分判商咧，其實西九亦都未必全部知道曬。如果西九選擇去做嘅時候咧，選擇去直接同啲分。
分判商係有一個誒誒誒直接找數咧關係咧，亦都係選擇誒唔係全部嘅分判商啊，係部分嘅分判商。另外咧，我諗亦都唔係喺誒建築界一個常見嘅情況咧，就係佢哋啲數咧通常係會到到誒，我唔係話佢拖數，不過係喺個誒傾。
嘅過程中咧，啲數先慢慢浮現出嚟嘅。咁所以我諗咧，直至西九同佢哋對數全部係完畢曬對曬啲單咧，先至可以下一個判斷，究竟西九管理局係咪曾經誒做過一啲你所指控嘅嘢咯？因為佢正如阿柏志高先生講，佢哋。
你定係佢講咩你就信曬？你畀秘書長答答辯嗱。我諗咧呢一個咧誒民政事務局或者政府同西九嘅關係咧係兩重嘅。咁喺二零零八年咧，當我哋成立咗西九管理局作為一個誒獨立嘅法定嘅組織嘅時候咧，佢本身係一個法人嚟嘅。噉我哋咧作為一個誒。
嗯，誒政策局咧係對佢有一個總體嘅監察，但係總體嘅監察唔等於一個美觀嘅管理。但係當然咧，誒民政事務局長、發展局長同埋係財經及副務局長咧，三位都係西九嘅董事局成員。噉我哋嘅同事咧亦都有分別坐佢唔同嘅小組嘅。咁喺嗰啲地方咧，我哋就。
就住西九管理局提供嘅資料咧，亦都會係時不時同佢哋喺個會上邊，同埋會與會之間咧，係同佢有不同層次嘅同事咧，係有誒即係誒要求攞資料啦、澄清啊、討論嘅。噉我諗整體而言咧，我哋同西九嘅聯絡係非常之密嘅。誒跟。
哦，多謝主席。噉啊，當然而家面對呢一個嘅爛攤子，即係爛攤子。當然我哋要面對一個善後嘅問題，亦都係一個過程中嘅問題。因為當而家見得到嘅情況就係西九管理局咧，其實喺呢件事上邊更負責無旁貸，因為你誒新窗嗰個嘅財困，大家。
好。
where they。
邊位回應咧？
There comes a point where you can no longer.
Mr. Chairman, the announcement that triggered our
was indicative of the fact that they were no longer solvent.
indicated that they had defaulted on the payment of a 300 million US dollar bond.
Action was made by Sin Chong to the stock exchange on May 18th.
which triggered a further default on a further I think is 150 million US dollar bond.
That clearly, and we've reported all this in our previous paper, which was submitted to this joint subcommittee in August.
carry a main contractor and that was the situation that we identified following that May 18th date.
知道點算好啦？可能中間有啲錢搞掂咗，有啲錢未搞掂，都仍然未答我問題。究竟西九，我當你係大老細，你爭人幾多錢，你自己掌唔掌握到啦？第二就係頭先我所講二零一六年知識呢件事，呢個係咪一個誒真實嘅陳述咧？唔該，主席。
about something like February March of two thousand and seventeen. That was, as we again have already explained, intended to ensure that the subcontractors had confidence that they would be paid for work done, and that approach has, I think, ensured that the project going. But
Having said that, we were concerned about their situation prior to that, and again, as we indicated in our previous paper to members, we took action to pay some of the key subcontractors directly from the middle of 2017.
大家當然知道啦。我用一個最即係可能誒最簡單嘅問題，可唔可以由誒即係西九幫手講講成個橫完少少時間畀我哋聽聽？你哋幾時知識財困溝個傳媒鎖子？你哋就話啊，二零一六年我哋知㗎啦。去到而家二零一八年十一月期間，你哋做過啲乜？採取過啲咩行動？而最重要就係，究竟？
點解喺關鍵嘅時間冇去選擇同公眾？即係嗱，佢冇佢同佢冇一個適切嘅時間同公眾通報啦。我哋係去去近乎係爆煲之後就知道，哦，我哋而家係誒，即係出現咗呢個財，即係嗰個嘅啊，建造商有個財困嘅問題啦，有五百幾個嘅分判商而家唔知。
Mr. Chairman, as I say, we we started this process in 2017. In fact, the information about Sinchong's financial difficulties was public knowledge. They had been making various statements to the stock exchange all the way through 17 and early 18.
The question, I think, is better directed at Xinjiang. How much do they owe?
We simply cannot do that. Otherwise, we fall foul of the stock exchange rules.
However, of course, we must take steps to protect the interests of the authority, and that is what we did.
那係某啲，Sinchong必須接受作佢哋嘅責任，under the terms of their contracts。那係個現實。
咁但係咧，你哋咧又要求佢哋揾律師。喂，你哋揾律師睇下，你哋同亞視達嗰份合約係咪一份真嘅合約？
所以是 not for us. Let me stress this. It is not for us to make statements regarding the financial situation of a publicly traded company.
講就係話喂，最初咧就金門或者你哋成立嗰間公司咧，就好熱情地咧叫佢喂快啲翻嚟啦，簽份合約啦。但係當佢知道佢咧已經完成到即係差唔多九成percent，甚至乎接近完成嘅時候咧。
完成餘下嘅工程，噉我都想局方咧，睇下可唔可以解釋更多有關嘅即係細節啦。係咪所有嘅細盤咧都願意轉移去到金門嘅建築咧？因為據我瞭解，其實我都收到一啲嘅即係承判商嘅求助。第一，
你未問嘅咩？即係你呢幾個月其實發生緊件事噉，主席你略略掌握到少少，起碼有個約數啩係嘛？我我要控制好嘅時間，因為個個啲超時咧太緊要啦。咁咧，如果唔係我哋今日咧就誒講講唔完，我哋第二個議題㗎。劉國芬兒。
問你哋去即係點樣計算翻啲錢？咁所以我好關注嗰個交接個工程其實係咪順利嘅，而呢一部分係咪會涉及到令到嗰個Ample咧係會超支同埋會誒延期嘅。
噉就好似就即刻懶待咗佢，咁咧佢都想問喂，咁而家你懶待佢唔緊要啦，噉佢係咪可以即係離場收錢咧？咁咧我知道嘅係好多分派商其實同緊新窗嗰個姊妹公司叫亞視達，其實係簽咗約嘅。
但係而家我哋面對係一個公堂嘅使用問題啊，主席。呢個係一個好嚴肅嘅問題。事實上，而家咧誒，我我頭先我都係未聽到個問題，究竟即係西九掌唔掌握到自己爭完幾多錢啦？其次，我想加多個問題，大家知道其實由頭到尾咧，而家成嚿嘅西九project咧，究竟超支幾多咧？都仲係好似仲係喺埋。
單找數嘅過程，我諗你淨係問咗我，等佢答你第一個問。好，我明白。個個都超時超得咁緊要嘅咧，唔緊要，我喺四分鐘內。唔該，謝謝方人名處先。你即係話要加多個問題啦，不如你淨係啊，Mr Pascal，你答一答佢。Mr Chairman， the question as I understand is how much do we owe? Of course, we're paying our bills and we have paid our bills all the way through.
多謝主席。我想問咧，而家即係啊金門咧就接咗呢個新窗啦。噉我亦都想瞭解下而家個交接工作係點嘅，因為文件提及到咧，管理局而家向完成工程所需要嘅現有分判商係發出咗六十三份跟替合約同埋轉移契約。
It's not to gammon.
新鴻，We don't change those terms.
但係，我想問個延期同埋超支嗰度係點咧？
Mr. Paskot, Mr. Chairman, a couple of things here. First, there are a number of subcontractors that we're not novating.
即係誒揸車去嘅時候點樣去法？咁呢啲我希望之前做，因為誒高鐵站開嘅時候，我發覺有好多指示牌都係唔係咁清晰，搞到啲遊人就唔方便嘅。
咁誒，我哋如果由廣東道啦，或者係誒高鐵站望過去咧，誒喜谷中心係好觸目嚇，好多遊客啊，或者香港市民睇到覺得好靚。
If we go out for a separate contract, and there will be other contracts that need to be signed, those terms are different. But the terms that we take on through innovation are exactly identical. There's no change, and we accept all the liabilities arising from that.
咁所以大家都好期望，即係佢能夠開放啦嚇。咁開放之後，佢唔一定去睇誒表演啊，佢可能去參觀下都好。所以我想問下咧，即係戲曲中心正式對外開放嘅時間，即係誒市民遊客可以參觀嘅時間係幾時？
即係你知道，可能每間嘅即係成板商個風格都唔同啊嘛。咁當初佢哋報畀呢一個嘅新窗嘅價，同報畀金門嘅價可能唔一樣嘅喎。咁所以有好多咧，而家我知道咧，仲係棘住緊，都未真係過曬佢嘅。咁第二咧，有啲咧就係同我。
喂，其實係咪真嘅合約？我相信你哋係好容易係自己佢查證得到，或者佢向新槍又好，或者瞭解翻得到嘅。我想問噉樣做嘅工作係咪似乎係刁難緊一啲嘅即係分判商咧？要佢哋要證明翻同即係新槍啊、亞視達嗰啲合約係咪真？作佢。
notably those that have finished their work, those that were previously directly under Sinchong, and there are a number. For example, Sinchong Asta, we're not novating. There are obvious reasons why we're not novating those. For the remainder, we are working it through the process. And let me stress, the novation is to bluepole.
They work for Bluepolls. They don't work for Gammon. They are supervised. They are managed by Gammon, and that's the arrangement that we've put in place. Gammon in this context will have its own subcontractors for certain types of work that either had not yet been contracted out previously by Sinchong, or for those subcontractors who choose.
And let me stress the word choose, not to come across, because they would rather do something else. We will have to replace them. But where we make an offer, it's for them to choose. We can't force them to accept innovation. As I said earlier in my reply to an earlier question, three parties have to sign up: the subcontractor, Sinchong has.
要certify， they release them from their contract with them and then blue poles， and that's the arrangement。 so it is a very different set of of agreements。 let me also stress that innovation means that we accept all of the the terms of the contract that were signed between the subcontractor and and
啊，可唔可以簡單答一答？As again, as I've answered earlier, we have given Gammon until December to come up with a detailed assessment of the need for any additional time for this project, and to come up with any costs that they would anticipate for the completion of the contract. And let me stress, at
at the moment， we're still working on opening the museum at the end of 2020， as we have been for the last couple of years. We've not changed those dates。咁如果係噉，可唔可以二十二月之前咧，你得到個數字咧，就即時向大家公佈咧？因為我哋下次嘅會議一月嘅，咁所以我希望你可以喺十二月得悉會唔會超支或者延期嘅時候咧。
唔該，主席。
在附近嘅
會 be available in the site.
啲咁使到去即係誒參觀嘅人又好，或者睇表嘅人又好，都能夠有基本嘅需求能夠滿足得到咧嚇，呢個問題。
咁誒，如果啲有人喺外面影相咧，佢周圍嗰個有關嘅空間足唔足夠畀人哋喺嗰度活動嘅，或者綠化嘅安排點樣咧？係。
嗱，誒，我哋其實超緊時啦，所以咧，我亦都喺呢度畫條線，亦都冇第二輪發言啦。咁咧，我仲有兩位，連埋我咧就三位。咁咧，而家係請阿郭家麒議員。
That's it. I'm good.啊，如果有依個資料嗰陣時啊，我都希望啊，Mr.Pasford可以盡快。Mr.Chambers，I will obviously publish what I can，but a lot of this is contractual，so we may not be able to。好，跟住係姚思榮議員。誒，多謝主席，我想問戲曲中心嘅嚇噉。
咁另外就係誒，因為我去嘅時候即係好多指示牌就唔清晰嘅，即係點樣入去咧？包括由誒高鐵站過去啦嚇。咁誒呢啲誒安排咧，唔知道你哋會唔會同有關嘅部門傾點樣處理嗰個指示牌嘅安排，亦包括誒。
誒另一個就係誒有關誒內部設施啦嚇，咁如果誒遊人入到去嘅話，咁可能佢哋就係想瞭解多啲誒機構中心嘅資料啦。咁唔知道有冇一個誒小型嘅展覽，畀遊人能夠知道入面嘅誒設施啊，或者佢誒誒有關嘅誒資料。
料或者有啲甚至嗰啲誒項目嘅介紹，咁使大家能夠清晰啲。咁入面咧，即係正常嚟講啊，一你你開咗之後咧，周邊嘅誒設誒餐飲或者一啲嘅小賣部咧，誒應該周邊嘅未有嘅。咁入面有冇類似呢啲誒餐飲或者小賣部設施？
Mr. Pass, yes, thank you, Mr. Chairman. Thank you for the question. Seichi Centre will open on the 20th of January. That's already been announced. However, there will be a soft opening, as we're calling it, from the end of December, where we will invite people to come in to help us to finalise that.
Last push to get the centre ready. Already, as we indicated on the presentation, the atrium is more or less completed, and people are already visiting and can visit the ticket office. But we're really not encouraging them to do so because there is still work going on, and certainly.
In certain areas, we still require everybody on the site to wear hard hats, so it's restricted access at the moment. But by the end of December, I would expect us to be able to open more of the facilities for public visitors. In terms of the signage, yes, in fact, we are talking to highways and to MTR. That is something that we're.
working on at the moment, and we hope to improve with support from government. And I have to say, CEDD have been very, very good on this, giving us some some advice. So I want to say thank you. In terms of providing information about the facilities, we intend to host guided tours that can be booked online, preferably.
also in the site, so that we will escort people through the centre. They'll have a chance to go behind the stage, behind the curtains, to see what happens, as well as into the tea house, the main theatre, seminar rooms. And we will also be using that as an opportunity to explain a little bit more about the different art forms.
That will take place on the site. Finally, you asked about catering facilities. There are a number of catering facilities from restaurant cha cha tang, coffee shops. All of those will be opening again between December and January February of next year. So by the time we open, catering
Yes, I believe the the area around has been upgraded and landscaped. The landscaping is now open. We don't restrict access to that. There will be wonderful opportunities in the site for photos, particularly in the H.M. I think it's a spectacular space, and indeed we.
We have been taking a series of photographs ourselves to document the progress on the site, and we've identified a number of locations in and around the site which give very good views of the C2 centre. So yes, I believe there should be enough opportunity for people to take photographs inside and in.
同埋係。
呢個係一個政府嘅主要工程。
誒時序咧，其實喺二零一六年十一月咧。
誒，大部分嗰啲未找數嘅誒。
分判商咧就已經將個名單咧係畀管理局，呢個第一。
咁大家都知道咧，其實西九咧，而家已經變咗係一啲尾大不掉。
搞唔掂之後咧，揾咗新嘅承辦商咧。頭先我聽到阿柏志高講，我覺得。
第二個咧，就係我聽到啲分判商佢哋管理嗰個做法都幾似啲黑社會嘅手法。
我覺得真係你，你都如果有少少廉恥嘅話咧，你都唔應該噉樣對待呢啲分判商。我睇翻政府嘅。
就其實西九由開始到而家咧，都係不斷嘅大話嚟嘅。十年前同我哋攞二百一十六億。
噉我唔問啊柏志高，因為佢聽唔到，佢都好難會預計佢會講真話。不過我想問咧，啊秘書長。
咁而家啲最少啦，即係嚟揾個誒，我哋去希望可以解決嘅就係最少七間七千萬。
我記得政府拍心口話唔會超支，而家超到離曬譜，一倍都唔止，仲要將嗰啲餐飲啊送畀佢。
即係揾曬自己人啊！即係連個總裁其實都係退休公務員，大家都知道。但係最難堪咧就係今次嘅事件，即係話喺新窗咧係嗯。
第二咧就係當然咧，就而家管理局揾咗新嘅主承辦商金門去做啦。咁承辦而家金門就揾咗佢自己嘅分判商。咁而家我哋見到有一紮咧，就係嗰啲叫孤兒嘅，即係話係做咗嘢出咗行水，甚至攞埋其實佢哋要打本嚟做嘅。
爭三千萬就第一次咧，就西九其實你有應佢嘅。你話好冇收三百萬就算咁個分判商話唔得喎，找唔到數噉啊。第二次咧就話不如加到添啲啦，添到五百八十萬。你同我籤一張秘密協議咧，我就算啦噉。
啊，李處長。
勞工處長嘅，亦都。
你會唔會滿意？
管理局係要公平公正對待呢一啲分判商，否則嘅話咧，政府係最大嘅無量。
管理局或者柏志高先生到到而家嘅做法，如果唔滿意嘅話，政府係咪應該責無旁貸，係督促？
我唔係僱主，係最大嘅無良嘅一個一個商人。你因為呢一單嘢咧，其實所有人咧都係被拉落水嘅，但係主事嘅係政府。
科數，甚至用一啲類似，即係我覺得都唔係好正常嘅手法咧，去講數啊，收少啲啊噉。你對於呢一啲噉嘅亂象咧，你嘅睇法係點？
政府咧就都不斷講咧，就係要公平、公正、公正去對待即係所有人啦。咁而家咧就最少七個分判商咧，就政府欠咗佢七千萬。其實呢啲資料咧就係早喺二零一六年已經出咗嚟十一月，但係政府不斷即係唔係政府啦，管理局不斷拖。
誒多謝郭議員嘅問題，更加多謝你關心西九呢個誒誒計劃啦嚇。咁誒我都同意西九對香港係非常之重要嘅。咁講翻個二百一十六億咧，大家記得喺零八年批嘅時候咧係未有而家呢個設計嘅。咁其實呢個西九文化區咧由誒計劃啦。
設計跟住工，阿秘書長冇乜時間啊！你答咗我，而家佢因為期間係關乎二十年嘅，咁喺呢十年二十年入邊咧，環球嘅投資環境啊，同埋誒建築成本嘅上揚等等咧，我諗呢啲都係我哋要誒考慮嘅因素。咁至於你問到建築嗰個咧，容許我講多兩句啦，即係我曾經咧係做過。
誒親自處理嘅不少喺建築界嘅嘢㗎，咁大家要明白咧，嗰個誒誒合約關係、嗰個法律關係咧，係喺個主要承建商同分判商之間嘅，亦喺個建築界咧分判到四至六層係一啲都唔罕見嘅。咁所以大家而家見到嘅嘢咧，係一個過程中嘅期間嘅。因
因為咧，你都唔知個分判裝再分判多幾多層，直至你同佢傾嘅時候，啲單慢慢慢慢先浮出嚟嘅。咁所以希望大家知道咧，而家係有人揾你哋協助，或者而家啲嘢咧係未完全係啲數一清二楚。呢個其實係一個誒唔係好驚奇嘅喺建築界係頗常態嘅。跟住你講翻係咪政府益自己有？
係退休公務員，冇錯，柏志高先生係退休公務員，但係大家唔好唔記得咧，佢第三任嘅行政總裁，頭兩任咧係全球招聘嘅。咁基於即係我唔再重複發生咗咩事，咁後來就阿柏志高先生咧先至任咗總裁嘅。咁誒，我哋同西九嘅關係咧，容許我用一個詞匯去講咧，就係話合作。
與監察，我哋中間咧嘅討論，誒有有多時有和諧，但係有多時都頗有火花嘅嚇。咁所以咧，我我仍然講咧，就喺柏志高先生任期之餘咧，係其實我哋最重要，我哋見到啲硬件係陸續起緊嘅。咁所以，我覺得咧，誒西九呢幾年嗰個誒進展係唔錯嘅。咁當然咧。
誒，當你話到誒誒，而家噉嘅做法係唔係誒誒誒對我哋用公堂唔負責咧？噉我覺得呢個誒，我睇唔到呢個問題出現咯。因為我哋其實誒監察緊嘅進度咧都幾嚴緊嘅。譬如啊，應總監同埋佢嘅上一手咧，其實咧都入埋佢誒。
西九入邊嘅發展小組嘅咁嗰啲誒硬件嘅工程嘅策劃啊等等咧，都跟得妥貼嘅。咁當然而家見到嘅問題咧，係我哋大家都唔想唔樂意係出現嘅。咁但係大家明白咧，新窗作為一個上市公司，除非係到到一個我哋覺得係不可挽回嘅地步咧，唔會行到而家。
嗯，Mr. Pescott，真係大啦。
action legally, so caution yourself when you speak, because those are very complicated project which goes into years of litigation.
第二樣嘢，我就啊常畀你解釋嘅關於呢個建築嘅情況咧，係好普遍。噉啊，普遍之中嘅咧，就係。
grounds in here now that you have more or less finished the superstructure work, so again good work and I congratulate you on the beautiful city building there. I passed through there last night, was really beautiful. Thank you.
希望大家明白，從政府嘅角度嚟講，甚至對西九管理局嘅角度嚟講，如果我哋有冇咩動機令到呢個計劃係誒困難，令到出現噉嘅問題咧，相信大家明白，我哋都唔想見到咯嚇。
要檢討，有時唔係淨係喺你哋依個方面出出出現咗有啲噉嘅問題，就算喺西九裏誒依個西九站好依個誒沙中線都有依個問題，所以或者政府真正要好好地檢討誒。
一步嘅，而期間大家當然話：嗯，如果你哋二零一六一七年咧早啲做就更加好啦。但係大家知道咧，佢作為一個上市公司，我哋亦都唔想做任何嘢係影響到呢間公司，而佢係倒轉告政府嘅。亦都有一樣嘢，如果我哋將呢一樣嘢係誒所謂prematurely係喺佢未到到我哋一個。
個認為係不可挽回嘅時間去公佈的話，其實嗰度一定對個工程進度咧係有影響嘅。正如我上次個會議講咧，其實一個兩難，係密切監察咗年紀咧先至痛下呢一步嘅。因為期間大家都見到，就算佢同新窗終止咗合約咧，都其實有一段時間要停咗工，直至到話。
揾到金門呢一個所謂management contractor一個負責幫佢管理，幫呢間獨立公司blue post管理呢個時候咧，先至可以喺九月再開翻工嘅。噉啊，唔係，就喺十月開再開翻工。咁希望咧，大家明白咧，即係期間咧，呢一個咧係一個好難嘅決定，而個決定咧係會影響個進度嘅。咁所以希望。
石禮謙議員，主席，誒，張學，多謝你。誒，阿郭家麒講咧講話，上一項我二十一個二十一點六個billion嗰陣時咧，喺立法會嗰陣時做過一個自己一個研究咧，係唔夠嘅嗰陣時，已經講咗係冇可能做到嘅，即係大家要睇翻啲文件喺度先第一樣。
啲尤其是喺一個你哋點佢哋點批啲合約嘅咧，係最低嗰個誒有兩個順風嘅呢兩個順風嗰時又是第一個想講關於嗰個technical ability嗰個咧，當時嗰陣時係好好，但係嗰個關於另外順風係幾多邊個去最低標攞到嗰個依個咧應該。
Duncan， having worked for you for so many years， I have great faith in you to deliver West Kowloon Cultural District project. It's not easy project. This is a project involving such massive construction work， arts and orders. So keep keep up the good work and do what you.
feel is right. Secondly, I caution you: you need not speak too much regarding the construction, because contracts liability goes into litigation and possibly arbitration. What you speak here and what you can speak here can only would not give you any protection.
secondly, I think that even now that you ask a management contractor to do it, it's very difficult for you to control cost because it's possibly, possibly. I do not know the details. You going for an open account book. An open account book, you have taken up a liability.
Be very careful and don't really try to tie the two together. Okay. Thank you.
你哋誒做咗啲咩功夫？啊嗱，因為最近我哋都聽好多咩？
西九為我哋可以帶嚟一啲高質素嘅啊文化藝術嘅表演嘅。
We prepare for these meetings very carefully into what we say. And secondly, thank you for your comments about the CQC centre. I think it will be a spectacular building.
啊，或者其他各方面咧，就進行一啲推廣。咁其實咧，我自己都有去過。而家局部係開放咗嘅，譬如戲曲誒中心周圍啦。
Can I can I just say one thing? Can I say thank you, both for the warning, which I take very seriously, and I have said before, I never say anything here unless we've thought it through before we come here.
噉啊，而家其實啊，好多不同地方嘅旅客啦，都有問我哋嚟西九啊點樣去啊？去到有啲咩睇啊？啊，咁所以我就想問一問喺安排上邊？
非常強嘅-liability of cost overrun. I also caution you, don't put a target date on this M plus, because if you put a target date on this M plus, you are actually pushing yourself to over budget, because everything is possible as long as you have money. But if you put a target date,
Then you be very very careful because you're putting the burden onto the the contractor, the management contractor. So be very careful. We had experience, borrow the experience from MTR, being a director there. I suggest that this is something you can share because you're uncommon.
啊！我我最後咧想問主席啊，對唔對？我少少時間。I also advise you to separate the continue construction of empass and the seventy million dollars 啊啊啊 issue， because it's two issues. So don't lumping together. This is something you have to be.
即係話響介紹誒有關西九發展嗰陣時咧，我哋睇到個環境好好嘅嚇，咁所以誒我自己我亦都知好多市民咧都期待即係可以盡快去西九咧誒參觀一下，享受一下。咁誒亦都希望將來咧即係。
逼爆東湧啊！逼爆邊度啊！咁第日一個好嘅地方，咁一定會有一有一啲人咧，將佢作為一個旅遊項目嘅。噉你哋會唔會預先有一啲安排咧？咁喺推廣嗰方面咧，誒，譬如會唔會誒，或者開始咗未同旅遊發展局？
噉，但係好多人咧都唔唔知點去啊。咁同埋誒四周圍嗰個交通咧，而家都係有少少亂嘅。咁或依響依方面，你哋可唔可以做多啲功夫？唔好話戲曲中心一開幕啦，其他嗰啲一路路發展啦。咁個個咧就因為一啲混亂嘅情況。
嗰個混亂咧，有可能就係由不清楚嚟到引發出嚟嘅啊，噉啊又鬧嘅啦嚇噉，所以啊或者啊Mr.Pescott，你可唔可以就住誒依幾方便畀一啲誒你哋做緊嘅功夫，或者將會做啲咩功夫嗰個計劃畀我哋咧？
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. In fact, we we we will be coming back with a more detailed brief on this subject. But let me briefly touch on the key issues. First and foremost, we're working with highways and with transport department to improve access. For example, we expect by later this month, if not earlier next month.
書長介紹一下有關今日嘅文件，好嘛？
啊，係咪啊，Mr. Pasco介紹啊？啊，啊，Louis，Louis長係，係主席，多謝，我而家開始。
由《 bye-laws》來 govern the operation of the public open space，包括公園，所以所有這些條款都已經在位。
邀請咧係按戲行嘅習俗咧，為大劇院係開台做六個大封上嘅嚇。咁現在咧，我請誒管理局咧係誒用一個powerpoint去介紹個進展嚇。
There will be a direct minibus route into the district that will improve access from Jim Sajee. Obviously, we're hoping that members will vote the money to allow us to put the Artist Square Bridge in, which will significantly improve access from the elements and therefore from the Tongcheng Line and the Airport Express Line. We
Also have mentioned already that we're building the subway connection to link in the Austin Road subway station to the C2 centre. Again, that will significantly improve access to the site. And finally, we're looking at putting in some ferry piers, possibly two, which will.
Allow us to tap into government's initiative in terms of inner harbour ferry services, which we think will provide a really wonderful way for the public to access the site. The second issue on promotion, yes, we are already in discussion with the tourism board. In fact, I briefed the MIC.
Group recently, we are focusing at the moment, of course, on the Seichi Center opening, and we've been doing a lot of promotion both here and in the mainland and elsewhere to look at marketing the opening events for the Seichi Center. In due course, as other facilities open.
Then the marketing exercise will expand and develop to ensure that not only people are aware of what we do. I'll give you an example. We're about to open a new exhibition, Naguchi for Jean Vou, which will be shown at the M Plus Pavilion from the fifteen th of this month. We.
We've been marketing and promoting that domestically as well as overseas. And finally, for example, we have been using free space, which happens every second weekend in the month during the winter months, to get people familiar with the site and knowing how to get there. So again, I would encourage.
If they want to come along this Sunday from two o'clock onwards, we'll have performances, jazz, classical music, as well as marketplaces. These are ways for people to get familiar with the site even before we open up. Finally, we already have in place legislation approved by the Legislative Council in terms.
Thank you。咁呢個議程咧就到此為止。噉我哋而家咧進入下一個議程，就係戲曲中心發展嘅最新進度。噉啊，首先啊，我知道有可能有一兩位啊西九嘅代表咧會轉一轉嘅。噉啊，響同時咧，不如我請阿秘書。
誒好簡單講，誒主席，誒西九文化區嘅戲曲中心咧，將要喺明年一月二十號咧係隆重開幕嘅。咁會成為文化區首個主要表演藝術嘅場地，係西九發展一個重要嘅里程碑。戲曲中心嘅啟用咧，我哋相信係有助培育年輕人誒。
年青新秀同埋支援新創作，為咗傳承同埋發揚戲曲藝術咧，係會增添動力嘅。咁西九文化區管理局咧已經安排咗一係列嘅開幕季嘅節目嘅，包括開幕演出粵劇經典《再世紅梅記》、香港粵劇商會嘅好戲連場《何新歲》誒會聚經。
京昆等劇種嘅中國戲曲啊，誒同埋戲曲家協會咧，亦嘅梅花獎嘅藝術團嘅摺子戲咧，亦都會有專場嘅。咁同埋我哋都會安排，正如柏志高先生剛才講嘅，導賞團同埋教育專場。咁喺今年十二月三十日咧，係香港百和會館咧，將會應西九管理局嘅邀。
我而家同大家誒介紹下戲曲中心誒開幕節目嘅進度啦。誒在座嘅除咗我之外咧，仲有我哋戲曲節目誒主管鍾珍珍女士啦，同埋我哋喺誒市場同埋票務呢方面嘅總監賈景龍先生嘅。噉我簡單咁介紹下我哋開幕嘅節目之後咧，我就會誒將誒。
誒，我就會交畀誒賈景龍先生咧，同大家講下我哋開幕節目，尤其是喺票務嗰方面嘅安排係點樣樣。咁喺大家嘅枱面裏邊咧，已經有一份咧，我哋嘅開幕誒節目嘅小冊子。咁喺個小冊子裏邊咧，已經好詳細咁講咗我哋個開幕嘅節目嘅嘅介紹係點樣樣，簡單。
翻嚟要講咧，我哋就首先係我哋喺十二月三十號開始有一個開台日，同埋跟住之後咧，我哋有一個誒開幕季嘅安排。我哋戲曲中心嘅場地租務咧，其實已經喺今年五月開始咧係公開詢誒，畀公眾詢問我哋嘅場地嘅租務。
去到而家為止咧，二零一九年嘅場地租務咧，我哋已經確切噉樣誒接受咗嘅租訂咧，已經有超過二十個，有二十個租訂咧喺二零一九年咧已經confirm咗。咁誒，我哋喺誒頭先誒，議員有提問，我哋幾時先至可以公眾入嚟？其實我哋喺
嗯。
啊！
咁先。
And encouragingly, we had 95% of those people register for tickets online.
在已經係推出緊一啲特別嘅票務安排，係為我哋戲曲中心嘅開幕。誒，pass主要經理，嘉景龍先生。
要給 as many people as possible access to the tickets， and it's been very successful. We had 28,000 people enter the ballot.
the vast majority of people who registered for tickets were from Hong Kong, but we also had registrations from the mainland, Macau, Taiwan, Singapore, USA and the UK.
喺十二月三十號咧開始咧，我哋就會有開台日，跟住咧我哋會有一個局部開放嘅一個安排，即誒同埋一個開放日嘅安排。咁喺個票務嘅安排嗰方面咧，一陣間同事都會係介紹誒。咁跟住我哋會喺一月二十號咧係正式我哋做一個Grand Opening。
喺一月二十號之後咧，我哋就誒戲曲中心咧就係全面開放。誒，我哋喺二月嘅時候，誒春節期間咧會有一連串嘅粵劇嘅演出。我哋喺三月嘅時候咧，我哋請到誒中國梅花獎誒藝術團嚟香港咧，就係同我哋誒呈現，包括京劇、昆劇、粵。
劇同埋評劇嘅唔同嘅劇種，咁誒簡而言之咧，其實喺誒開幕嗰個季度嘅安排，同埋誒喺誒戲曲中心嘅節目嘅介紹嘅安排裏邊咧，我哋係包含咗有免費節目，去到唔同價位、唔同價錢嘅節目，我哋亦都係目標嘅。
觀眾除咗有學生、有遊客、新觀眾、粵劇戲迷、京劇、昆劇，或者係其他劇種嘅戲迷，我哋都係會涵蓋得到，令到甚至係一啲朋友，只不過係入嚟參觀睇展覽、影張相、飲杯茶，唔同嘅。
節目咧，我哋都會有安排。再加上我哋甚至咧，我哋有同香港電影資料館係合作緊。我哋會喺開幕節目季裏邊咧，亦都會呈現一啲誒唔同地方嘅誒戲曲嘅一啲誒電影嘅作品喺裏邊。咁所以我哋亦都有導賞團啦，場地導賞團講。
幫助同埋工作方同埋一啲教育嘅專場嘅安排，咁依啲全部嘅資料咧，其實喺呢本書裏邊已經有，亦都係全面噉樣咧，喺我哋個網站裏邊咧，已經係畀大家呢方面嘅知識。好似頭先誒柏志高先生咁講，我哋已經同誒開始同旅遊業界啦、誒香港嘅學校同埋誒教育嘅團體。
啦，誒，我哋有同誒誒，貿易發展局佢哋一啲唔同嘅展覽，點樣可以推廣畀唔同嘅展覽商，或者係你我哋依個地方嚟到做一啲誒安排，或者係一啲演出誒嘅觀賞嘅安排咧，我哋全部都喺度傾緊。咁去到依度咧，我希我將時間咧係交畀。
畀誒Kingston我嘅同事就係同大家介紹咧，喺我哋開幕季裏邊，我哋點樣去誒計劃去應付一啲唔同嘅票務嘅要求。因為其實關於演出嘅票務喺過去呢一年裏邊都喺香港裏邊咧一個好大家好關注誒嘅一個題目。我哋都有詳細嘅考慮之後咧，我哋正
Okay, thank thank you very much. Just a little bit of an update on the on the ticketing. The first stage in the ticketing for the Westcrown Cultural District was that we opened the ballot for the tickets for the reincarnation of Wed Plum. Took place between the sixteenth and twenty eighth of October. We chose ballot because we believed it was the fairest way.
OK。
點算？
Okay.
thank you.
嗯。
係。
at the theatre.
apologies。
According to the waitlist.
或 in person with no transaction fee.
unsuccessful applicants will be added to a waitlist and we will allocate remaining tickets.
and just a reminder, all tickets that we sell online, by phone or in person have no transaction fee for customers, so we're doing everything we can to get people to buy online.
Yeah, so the successful applicants were selected by ballot by an independent third party that we used. This third party organisation were the same vendor who did the balloting for Hong Kong Philharmonic for the the concert a while ago, and we've now been contacting all the people.
Who were successful? We have over five five hundred tickets across nine performances that are available for public sale. And the next stage will be those successful applicants will be able to buy tickets from ten th to the eighteenth of November using a one time passcode, and they can buy them online by phone.
Okay, all the other shows go on public sell from twenty six November. That's all the ones that are listed in the brochure, and we also have free tickets that will be part of the soft opening. They'll be available from eleven December and they'll be distributed online and through organised groups. And we will also have a certain number available each day.
係，我哋介紹去到依度誒，歡迎大家嘅提問。OK，噉啊，報咗名嘅就有陳志全議員、毛孟靜議員同埋謝偉全議員。我哋都係用翻四分鐘啦，好嘛？首先嚟請陳志全議員。係啊，唔該主席。首先多謝西九邀請我哋戲局中心嘅開幕啦。其實我自己都係諗住畀錢買飛。
Mr. Pescott.
Let me deal with the ticketing and then I'll pass on to.
到時係點樣去分配？點樣去取捨咧？咁唔該，主席。
解決到大家同一時間要爭入去，即係。
啲咯，咁呢個係關於即係未來嗰個誒售票安排。其實呢個咁大型嘅設計，真係你生意好又煩，生意差又煩嘅。
哦，即係話使咗咁多錢起噉，佢坐下睇下，好似我喺北京大劇院都唔知佢做咩去旅行，噉就買張飛入去睇睇一次噉，叫做睇過啦。但係未來即係嗰個。
去支持嘅噉，細個頭先話有二萬八千個登記名登記咗啦。噉我都係其中一個，不過我係抽唔到嘅嚇。不過陳淑莊抽到，佢話可以同我一齊去。
Had we not instituted a system to try and ensure fairness, so it is simply simple as that. We want people to have a fair and transparent system, so they know that they apply. If they choose not to use their ticket,
先知係見真章㗎啫。誒，但係如果個競爭好大嘅時候，其實粵劇咁優先權嘅咧，咪唐英年話佢係三百幾種劇目咧，都想可以有機會喺我哋誒戲曲中心嗰度主演，咁即係。
爭入去即係鬥快上網去搶飛嗰個方法嘅，但係你話所謂炒飛咧，因為呢個購票權其實佢有咗，係咪理論上佢嗰個一次性購票密碼，即係佢哋寫嘅嚇，係佢哋咁寫，一次性購票密碼可以轉讓嘅係咪啊？佢可以，我攞到人個密碼，我咪可以上網買飛咯，誒？
其實而家抽嗰個咧係個購票權嚟嘅啫，即係購票權一個抽到個權咧就可以買四張飛。咁二萬八千個登記，噉你哋係有幾多人會誒中籤咧？同埋今次個開幕劇目在世紅梅記，咁有幾多係內部飛咧？內部飛你明我意思啦，即係可能主辦團體啊，佢哋或者可以內部影。
購有冇咧？其實喺呢個票目安排裏裏邊有冇一個大原則，即係有幾多飛佢可以誒係自己去去誒內部處理咧噉樣。同埋係咪每一個劇目透過佢嘅受歡迎程度而誒去設計嗰個誒購票方法？我相信唔會每個未來每
個劇目或者都係用翻呢個誒所謂抽售票權嘅方法嚟到去處理。我諗呢個其實佢嘅設計咧，我就覺得唔關炒唔炒飛事嘅，係費事大家一一開開嗰日咧，即係成個系統死曬，就話上唔到網啊，又鬧到咩都鬧曬啊。咁而家呢個方法係可以。
同埋你都唔係唔係實名制㗎嘛？誒，如果你話去嗰啲誒售票處買飛咧，佢就要有授權書啊嗰啲，我睇過你嗰啲。但係如果網上應該就唔使，你有嗰個密碼就可以買到。即係話，如果我有一班朋友，我都有叫咧，其實大家上網去即係去抽嗰個認購權，噉你抽到未？個機會率自然會大啲。
即係生意好咧，我再問你喂誒，而家你話誒未來一年有二十個租訂係confirm咗嘅，咁呢個係理想定定係一般定係點？因為第一季第二季我就唔好擔心嘅，即係新開幕，即係就算你唔理你做咩劇目，嗰啲人都會去，即係買張飛入去坐下感染下，即係嗰個。
就是 to answer the question on the the programming, the ticketing is a one off. We want we know there'll be huge demand. I mean, twenty eight thousand tickets applications for just five thousand tickets is a huge proportion. We have to manage that. I think we would have been totally open to criticism.
誒滿意嘅。
O.K.跟住係請胡孟正議員。
staff， we need people who are， for example， there for security reasons， for technical reasons。 so we do need a minimum number of tickets。 Louis， Louis，你等一等。
They get four for each successful. They only get four for each successful. Then of course we we can't control that. But I would have hoped, but through this mechanism, that it would be end users. And I emphasised that in the press conference that we held when we announced the arrangements. That this was intended for end users. This was not intended for third party to come in and.
Buy up large numbers, and the reality is for scalpers they lay they need large numbers to make it sustainable. But by only restricting it to four, we think it's reasonable. Secondly, in terms of concessionary tickets to the other organisers, yes, of course there are tickets available for them which we don't control. They control.
But we will be processed through the ticketing system. As far as internal things, in this case, I've insisted that we have the absolute minimum number of internal tickets, and it's less than 10 tickets per show that are reserved only for working staff. No one else can use those tickets, and we do need working.
好啊！誒，好似頭先誒柏志高先生所講誒，我哋今次呢一個售票嘅安排咧，係純粹因為今次係戲曲中心嘅開幕啦。而呢個劇目誒，一般嚟講，當任伯基金會喺以往嘅演出嚟講咧，都通常都會超過廿場或者係幾多。噉我哋都知道咧，今次會。
有好大嘅一個公眾嘅需求喺度。噉我哋誒最大嘅原則咧，我就真係唔想公公婆婆喺度要排好耐嘅隊嚟到做呢件事。咁所以咧，我哋誒考慮好多之後咧，我哋係淨係為今次咧有呢個噉樣嘅誒售票嘅安排。咁誒，關於內銷飛嗰方面咧，我哋而家其實～
係將六十嘅percent嘅大部分嘅飛咧係拎出嚟喺公眾嚟度賣，咁其他咧就係關係演出團體佢哋需要有一啲誒誒自己內部嘅一啲內消費嚟去做，咁所以咧可以同大家咁講咧係超過係我哋有五千五百張門票係超過係六十。
個percent嘅我哋嘅可有嘅門票咧，係其實咧喺公眾嘅方法咧嘅渠道嚟到出嚟賣。咁頭先誒議員有問過，而家租場嘅安排係點樣樣？咁而家我哋誒誒喺二零一九誒開幕嘅第一年裏邊咧，我哋而家已經confirm咗十二個啦，誒二十個啦，而二十個咧。
係當我哋個場地仲係起緊，仲係完未完全完工嘅時候咧，已經係confirm我哋嘅booking。我相信咧，當我哋場地開幕咗之後啦，或者係誒周邊啊個設施或者其他個完成完工咗之後咧，個市場嘅反應咧會仲好啲。咁以而家嚟講咧，呢二十個安排咧，我哋係相當之。
我係嘛？我係誒唔該，主席。嗱有一樣嘢咧，我到而家都不能釋懷嘅就戲曲中心喺香係香港嘅建設啊，亦都由香港人畀錢噉，但係英文名就叫C.C. Centre。你呢個真係好突兀啦！
尤其是係嗰個q u嗰個發音啊！啊，我係半個英文老師啦。q後面咧一定要有u嘅啊。英文上如果唔係發唔到音嘅，就譬如question啊、quest嗰啲嚇。咁但係而家咧，你q咧變咗ch嘅發音，噉你真係啊，外國遊客咧外頭嘅人。
我真係擔心不明所以嘅啦，咁但係我而家懷疑誒呢個問題咧，我係嘈咗幾年㗎啦，係已經十錘定音㗎啦，冇可能再改㗎啦嚇！你呢啲噉嘅罕物都忍曬，好咁呢個我就忍你，冇辦法啦，已經冇得嘈嚇。但係但係我見到你好。
多嘅劇目咧，你譬如《烏不歸》噉，我諗下死啊！英文係咪《烏不歸》咁咧？唔係喎，又嚇。Time to go home亦譯得幾好喎。但係咧更加唔仍然又唔接受啦。就係呢個萬世流芳張玉橋，我對粵劇嘅認識咧就麻麻地嘅啫。去網上。
睇一睇咧，原來係我哋嘅名旦啊，方艷芬嘅首本名劇嚟嘅，係粵劇嚟嘅。好咁呢個咧點譯咧？佢竟然話except from咩？佢叫The Immortal張玉橋嗱喂，好過分喎！張玉橋就應該唱喐Q。
第二樣嘢咧，我又想問下，即係話誒。
嘅拼音嚟誒，翻譯個名得唔得呢？
以後唔好咁得唔得啊？呢個逆左已經印咗就有你啦。
得唔得咧？以後唔好噉。喂，我哋有個Hong Kong identity，really。
應該去意見係收到一下，好，多謝。跟住係謝偉全議員。
誒，我想知道下，即係有關管理方面咧，有咩辦法可以減少啊嗰啲票嘅炒賣嗰個問題？呢個第一樣嘢。
呢度呢度香港嚟嘅，點解你噉樣要用普通話嚟譯我哋粵劇喺香港演出嘅劇目咧？呢個我覺得係啊過曬火位咯。
咁誒就頭先亦都講，可能係啱開幕咧，有啲表演咧好受歡迎嘅。咁誒有啲安排嚇，因應係需要嘅。咁誒，主席我其實想問下，即係如果真係好受歡迎嗰啲咧？
啊，Louis，誒，多謝你嘅意見。我哋會咁做嘅，因為我哋誒粵劇咧都係嶺南文化一一部分嚟嘅。咁所以誒，如果有一啲可以保留我哋誒，係啦，誒張玉橋啊，咩曾玉橋啊，但點樣點樣去翻譯咧？誒。
都市主席誒西九文化區呢個計劃咧，搞咗咁多年咧，最後咧而家即係個戲曲中心正式嚇，即係可以誒開幕畀誒服務香港嚇，提供呢方面嘅設施咧，咁當然咧就係好歡迎啦。搞咗咁耐。
啊啊，Louis，好啊！誒，多謝誒毛議員嘅意見。我哋而家咧都一路喺度誒檢討緊，我哋而家唔同嘅誒翻譯嘅方法係點樣樣。不過我可以喺度同大家分享下，其實誒誒粵劇或者係唔同嘅戲曲嘅翻譯嘅唔同嘅方法咧，喺過去嗰幾十年咧，喺香港或者係喺。
唔同嘅華文地區咧，都有一啲唔同嘅系統喺度翻譯緊。就算喺香港，以前喺誒電影，好似頭先我咁講，某一啲嘅粵劇咧，已經係翻譯咗做誒電喺拍咗部電影，有啲唔同嘅英文嘅改編或者唔同嘅英文嘅翻譯。我哋每次做一個決定嗰個劇，我哋翻譯嘅名係點樣嘅？
時候咧，我哋都會參考一啲唔同嘅來源，或者係喺佢喺唔同嘅地方呈現嘅時候嘅嘅誒嘅英文嘅翻譯嘅版本。咁所以咧喺唔同嘅劇嘅翻譯裏邊咧，可能會有唔同嘅安排。咁歡迎大家繼續畀意見我哋。誒，主席，我點都唔信張玉橋呢個方艷芬嘅手本。
名劇係由頭到尾，張玉橋係譯做曾於超㗎咯，真唔好玩啦！要譯嘅梗係廣東話嘅發音譯㗎嘛。你而家籠統咁答我，其實係冇答到我嘅問題。可唔可以以後啊係粵劇咧，你就真係跟足我哋廣東話嘅發音？
咁因為我對粵劇都有少少認識啦，咁有啲歷歷史嘅問題㗎啊，譬如有一啲因為過往咧都有誒好多公開嘅演出，或者喺海外公開演出，有可能個名咧已經譯譯咗出嚟㗎啦。我哋香，我哋廣東人都聽唔明嘅。如果不過呢個意見咧，我覺得誒。
將來啲體育中心咧就會開放租用啦嚇畀人哋。我係想了解下租用方面嗰個誒，我想管理方面係一定有個制度，或者某方面咧，即係會誒，即係容許啊，即係租用嚟誒表演嘅。咁呢方面可唔可以即係簡略啲講？
get the tickets.
都有啲唔同嘅，尤其是我哋而家唔係淨係香港嘅欣賞嗰啲觀眾嚇。
There's no boundary. It's international, so you should set a quota for them.
但係，它depends on who controls concession tickets, who controls the distribution, at which we don't control. That's the biggest problem in the in the ticketing field.
講最重要，即係等大家知道咧，即係要租用呢樣嘢咧，係誒，即係有咩基本嘅要求咧噉。咁至於租用嗰個費用啊，誒，我諗亦都講講，即係誒。
Yeah, thank you. I take the point. In fact, one of the reasons that we're encouraging people to apply online is there's no barriers. They can apply from UK, from the states, and as you see, we already have that evidence to show that it's it's working. I think that's the best way.
If you put them into the ballot of twenty eight thousand, they will be swallowed up. They will be never have a chance to come and participate. And I think that is only fair to that, and that's also to promote Hong Kong internationally. That's one point. The second point that this is one of the nicest.
即係可能有啲就係我諗個租金可能有唔同啦，我唔知啊呢方面可唔可以即係解釋一下咧？唔該，主席。好。啊，因為啊，Mr. Chairman，let me just briefly deal with the first one. Um, honestly, we're not in the business of being able to deal with a general problem of scalping. We will try our best to ensure that end users
My colleague reminded me that, for example, under the registration system, the balloting system, we expect people to turn up in person to get their ticket, to physically receive their ticket, and we can check their ID card that way. But for general sales, particularly if they're not our programming, it's very difficult to put those conditions on. So I cannot promise.
That we will be able to deal with scalping any better than government can. To be honest with you，主席，我呢度想補充，我明白嗰個困難程度咧。但係一方面亦都要平衡翻啦。頭先你可能誒有興趣欣賞嗰啲咧，唔係一定係香港嘅人啊嘛。你頭先講都有即係其他地方嘅人啊。咁呢啲咧，只不過係。
第一即係有去考慮，第二咧，亦都你會關注，你起碼知啊嘛。即係有啲就誒，即係我我希望啦嚇。即係如果真係有問題嘅時候，到時你係因應去一啲政策或者一啲措施去去做一啲嘢，就即係呢呢度呢度，我係最主要嘅啫。我明白每一樣嘢。
啊！盛禮謙議員，主席仲未答第二個問題。主席，我先答埋關於租務嗰方面。誒，關於租務嗰方面，我簡單同誒議員介紹一下。誒，戲曲中心咧，我哋誒對戲曲係會有傾斜嘅，咁戲曲係會比其他嘅誒租客咧，可以早兩個月咧向我哋提。
出誒租用嘅申請，意思就即係話誒。通常嚟講，譬如話你想租某一個日子喺之前嘅十六個月咧，我哋已經可以接受誒戲曲嘅租用嘅要求。咁去到兩個月之後，即係十四個月之前咧，我哋就可以接受其他嘅藝術嘅誒團體嘅要求。去到再兩個月之後。
即係話去到十二月之前咧，我哋就可以接受其他嘅要求。咁所以戲曲中心咧係會誒對戲曲同埋藝術會有唔同嘅傾斜。咁另外咧喺個租金嘅方面咧，戲曲嘅價格咧誒個租用嘅租金嘅安排咧，亦都係比其他咧會有一個好大嘅一個誒折扣出到嚟。噉啊，關於價格同埋最誒每
每一個唔同嘅場地嘅租金嘅安排咧，其實而家已經係公開喺網上係誒可以畀誒公眾嚟到查閲，同埋想租用嘅朋友咧都可以直接誒接觸我哋嘅同事㗎啦。好唔該，石禮謙議員。誒，First like first comment is on the balloting of the tickets of your five thousand tickets。
In your presentation, you have actually put on the board there that there are actually there's registration from Singapore, US, other places. I wonder whether you have a system setting a allocation for the overseas participants because I.
對。
Thank you.
OK。
building in Hong Kong.
你 have put into the booklet， despite the fact that you use potong wa。
啊！個欣賞或者認識咧，其實不比我哋啊香港人低啊或者少嘅。
the the operas you know just make sure that end users are those who really appreciate the issues you know as a matter of fact I've seen all the operas that
啊！我都非常之認同啊，石議員個意見嘅。啊，其實我哋好多時去外國啦，即係外國人對於粵劇。
Some of of the tickets available specifically for different groups, but that's something we'll look at. Yeah, the major supporter of Chinese opera, Cantonese opera, actually comes from
A way of putting that into the book, but as I tell you, it's really good to see how arts come back alive. It's a resurrection of traditional Chinese culture.
Over Hong Kong to really to return to its roots and build this building, so I suggest that is a humble request. Remember him for what he has done for Hong Kong.
complexity in simplicity. I a very humble request: the architect died in the job. Find a little corner to commemorate his greatness.
China towns around the world, and would be good to bring them back in. This is something that they have contributed to Hong Kong development of opera and arts, so they should be given some preference. Because if a lot of people just go and visit CQ, they don't need to attend.
That set up a new system for Hong Kong Cultural District. Whoever contribute greatly should be remembered. And the architect was one of the most famous Chinese in Canada. They got he got the the highest Canadian award. He came here.
Mr. Prescott, I thank the honourable member for that very, very generous suggestion. In fact, we will be doing exactly that. We have already identified a location. In fact, we had his wife here this weekend, and we explained to her exactly what we're doing, and we will be inviting her back to the opening. So we will.
會 definitely be doing that. As far as the overseas registration in this case, honestly doesn't really matter whether you're from Hong Kong or from overseas. You had exactly the same chance through the ballot to secure a ticket. But I will look at this for future and working with the tourism board to see whether there is indeed a value in having perhaps.
O.K.
Okay.
即係正話，我哋又講到誒，因為歷史嘅。
啊，粵曲啊文化咧，都都係有幫助嘅。
啊！各位啊，官員同埋啊，西九文化區嘅代表出席，噉啊。
依個項目就完結啦。咁有冇其他項目？有冇委員要提出其他項目？冇。咁咧，我就誒宣佈今日嘅會議結束。多謝各位。
誒問題有好多，以前已經做落咗㗎啦。但係我覺得，既然我哋西九係一個舉世矚目嘅誒文化藝術區，有陣時有啲嘢咧啊啱。
我哋就要做㗎啦，咁喺呢個時間嚟到研究一下、檢討一下咧，都都係適合嘅嚇。噉啊，我亦都希望，我期待戲曲中心嘅開幕啊，去睇翻場啊粵曲啊粵劇嚇。咁OK，噉啊今日咧就好多謝。
咁正話講到有一啲翻譯嗰度咧，一粵劇始終都係一個南方嘅嶺南文化嚟嘅。咁如果可以將誒誒廣東話啊等等呢啲因素咧，喺翻譯上邊啊做得誒更好咧，我覺得喺推廣啊粵劇。